# Claudia Negri Ribalta

☑ csnegri[at]uc.cl| claudia.negriribalta[at]uni.lu

## **Summary**

Accomplished academic, with experience in academic and professional research on the socio-technical impacts of new technologies, socio-technical requirements, and how to build privacy complaint and secure systems. Her main strengths lies in data protection, user-design, human and policy centered cyber security, requirement engineering and hypothesis building. Claudia's main area of research is the intersection between software engineering, data protection, user-centered design and governance. Other topics include the security and privacy requirements, requirement elicitation, the impact of technology in the evolution of socio-technical concepts, State surveillance, intelligence and cyber strategy and data protection legislation.

**Currently working as a research associate (post-doc)** at the "Interdisciplinary Research Group in Socio-technical Cybersecurity" (IRiSC) at the SnT, University of Luxembourg, and serving as the **president of OptIA**.

#### **Education**

09/2019–07/2023 **Doctorat en Informatique**, *CRI - Université Paris I Panthéon-Sorbonne*, École de Management, Paris, France.

PhD title- STAP: Socio-Technical dAta Protection framework for requirements with divergent mental models. Focused in studying the intersection between requirement engineering, data protection, socio-technical issues and new technologies. Supervisor: Camile Salinesi, co-Supervisor: Nicolas Herbaut.

04/2022– 09/2023 **Scholars programme -Cohort 3**, *The Europaeum*, Lead by the University of Oxford in collaboration with other European universities.

The Europaeum Scholars Programme is taken alongside a doctorate in 7-8 intensive modules, each of 3-5 days, in universities across Europe. The modules include seminars, debates, and workshops with leading academics and practitioners; professional skills training; and substantial teamwork. As part of the program, the project Portal2EU was conducted in a multidisciplinary group and presented as a policy proposal.

09/2017–09/2018 M.Sc - Interactive Digital Media - School of Computer Science, *Trinity College Dublin*, Dublin, Ireland (*Distinction*).

A program from the Computer Science and Statistics department. Skills acquired: programming (HTML, CSS, JavaScript, JQuery, Node.Js, SQL and basic Java), graphic design, user-interface design, website design, and 3D modelling. Thesis topic: "The difference between cyber terrorism and hacktivism" (grade: 1.1) - Final grade: 1.1 with distinction.

08/2010–12/2016 **Political Science, 5 years degree**, *Pontifica Universidad Católica de Chile*, Santiago, Chile (*one vote of distinction*).

Five year political science program, with majors in international relations and security. Worked as teaching assistant for four courses over 2 years. Participated in several student activities (student politics, student societies, Model United Nations and volunteering) and founded a non-profit organization (DiploLab).

Thesis topic: "Open Source Intelligence - analysis methods" - Supervisor: Ricardo Neeb

## Work Experience

09/2023–Present **Research Associate**, SnT, University of Luxembourg, Luxembourg.

Part of the laboratory "Interdisciplinary Research Group in Socio-technical Cybersecurity" (IRiSC) researching from an interdisciplinary perspective, with emphasis in requirements engineering, data protection and cibersecurity.

12/2020–Present **President and co-founder**, Observatorio para la transprencia e inclusión algórtimica (OptIA), Chile.

Currently president and co-founder of the NGO OptIA, which focuses on transparent and inclusive algorithms, and it's impacts in public policy.

11/2020–Present **Teaching staff for the course "Criptomonedas y Blockchain" (Cryptocurrencies and Blockchain)**, *Universidad de Chile*, Chile.

Part of the teaching staff of the introductory course on 'Cryptocurrencies and Blockchain'

01/2021 – 08/2023 **PhD researcher**, *Université Paris I Panthéon-Sorbonne*, France.

Part of the laboratory "Centre de Rechercher en Informatique" (CRI) researching about requirements for personal data protection, GDPR and other socio-technical challengeds for new technologies, under the direction of Professor Salinesi. Part of multiple academic publications, and conducting courses within the University and other higher level institutions on the topic. In the framework of a doctoral contract with the French Government and the Université Paris I Panthéon-Sorbonne.

04/2019–01/2021 Research Engineer and Cybersec Consultant, Almerys, France.

High level research into security, privacy, data governance and decentralized applications. Led Almerys' work in the H2020 CUREX project, for the working group "Privacy and Security Assessment and Cyber hygiene", "Requirements, System Design and Use Cases" and "Blockchain", and contributed in the H2020 PlasticTwist project. This included - but was not limited to - eliciting privacy and security requirements for blockchain, data protection impact assessment, carrying out cyber hygiene surveys, designing privacy compliant blockchain systems, market analysis, smart contract design, among others. Wrote and published several academic and professional publications on the topics of data protection, requirement engineering, GDPR and blockchain .Co-led the project management

08/2018–03/2019 IT Security Consultant, Grant Thornton LLP, Ireland.

Consultant on topics of privacy, data governance and cyber security. Creation of various privacy policies and notices, data protection risk analysis, restructuring of data protection management and containment of data breaches for external companies. Knowledge of OWASP, ISO 27000, BCM, Cobit and data protection. Audited companies over data breaches and data security events. Member of IAPP.

08/2015–07/2017 **Teaching Assistant**, *Universidad Católica de Chile*, Chile.

Responsible for tutoring and coaching sessions to ensure students' success on courses related to International Relations and Defense. Coordinated the end to end process of exams (creation, invigilation and grading). For details, see back.

11/2016–04/2017 **Intern- Dirección Antártica**, *Ministry of Foreign Affairs*, Chile.

Led and coordinated the cross functional efforts to publish the annual National Antartic document. Key member of the task force that wrote the executive decree National Policy for Antartica 2017. Created the division's public communication documents including newsletters, bulletins and speeches.

#### **Publications**

- [1] Rosa Velasquez, Claudia Negri-Ribalta, René Noel, , and Oscar Pastor. Exploring Understandability in Socio-Technical Models for Data Protection Analysis: Results from a Focus Group [upcoming]. 2023.
- [2] Claudia Negri-Ribalta, René Noel, , Oscar Pastor, and Camille Salinesi. *Conceptual Modeling for Common Ground in Interdisciplinary Work on Privacy* [upcoming]. Springer International Publishing, 2023.
- [3] Claudia Negri-Ribalta, René Noel, Nicolas Herbaut, Oscar Pastor, and Camille Salinesi. Sociotechnical modelling for gdpr principles: an extension for the sts-ml. In 2022 IEEE 30th International Requirements Engineering Conference Workshops (REW), pages 238–234. IEEE, 2022.
- [4] Claudia Negri-Ribalta, Nicolas Herbaut, and Camille Salinesi. Trusting the big brother inside my pocket: User-oriented requirements for contact tracing. In Jochen De Weerdt and Artem Polyvyanyy, editors, *Intelligent Information Systems*, pages 82–91. Springer International Publishing, 2022.
- [5] Claudia Negri Ribalta. A method to deal with social bias and desirability in ethical requirements. In J. Fischbach, N. Condori-Fernández, J. Doerr, M. Ruiz, and et al., editors, *Joint Proceedings of REFSQ-2022 Workshops, Doctoral Symposium, and Poster & Tools Track*. Springer International Publishing, 03 2022.

- [6] Claudia Negri Ribalta, Marius Lombard-Platet, Camille Salinesi, and Pascal Lafourcade. Blockchain mirage or silver bullet? a requirements-driven comparative analysis of business and developers' perceptions in the accountancy domain. In *Journal of Wireless Mobile Networks*, *Ubiquitous Computing*, and Dependable Applications (*JoWUA*), volume 12, 2021.
- [7] Mirko Koscina, Marius Lombard-Platet, and Claudia Negri Ribalta. A blockchain-based marketplace platform for circular economy. In *Proceedings of the 36th ACM/SIGAPP Symposium on Applied Computing, SAC 2021, Online.* ACM, 2021.
- [8] N. Six, C. Negri Ribalta, N. Herbaut, and C. Salinesi. A blockchain-based pattern for confidential and pseudo-anonymous contract enforcement. In 2020 IEEE 19th International Conference on Trust, Security and Privacy in Computing and Communications (TrustCom), pages 1965–1970, 2020.
- [9] Rose Esmander, Pascal Lafourcade, Marius Lombard-Platet, and Claudia Negri Ribalta. A silver bullet? a comparison of accountants and developers mental models in the raise of blockchain. In *Proceedings of the 15th International Conference on Availability, Reliability and Security, ARES '20, New York, NY, USA, 2020.* Association for Computing Machinery.
- [10] Mirko Koscina, David Manset, Claudia Negri Ribalta, and Octavio Perez. Enabling trust in health-care data exchange with a federated blockchain-based architecture. In *IEEE/WIC/ACM International Conference on Web Intelligence Companion Volume*, WI '19 Companion, page 231–237, New York, NY, USA, 2019. Association for Computing Machinery.

## Grantts, Scholarships and prizes

2022 **100 young Chilean leaders ("100 jóvenes líderes")**, Universidad Adolfo Ibáñez y El Mercurio.

Recognition as a young leader in the Chilean society

- The Scholars Programme scholarship, The Europaeum.Fully funded scholarship for the Scholars Programme from The Europaeum
- 2020 **IRB Student Grantt**, *Requirement Engineering*. Grant from the IRB for attending the RE'20 Conference
- 2019-2021 CIFRE Postgraduate Scholarship, CIFRE no. 2019/0502...

Funding from the French state, that consist of an agreement between the State, a University's doctoral school and a company.

# **Teaching details**

Teaching.....

This work consisted both giving short courses or being part of the academic staff of the different programs

2020 - present **Technical aspects of blockchain and cryptocurrencies**, *Postgraduate diploma on blockchain and cryptocurrencies*.

University of Chile

Part of the academic staff for the postgraduate dip loma on blockchain and cryptocurrencies. Taught the course Technical aspects of blockchain and cryptocurrencies. The diploma is usually given twice a year.

2022 - 2023 Introduction to programming - Python , First year MIASH, Université Paris I Panthéon-Sorbonne

TD of introduction to programming - Python, which included 2 hours weekly lab, creating and marking of labs and test. The course taught basic concept of programming, ending with recursivity.

2020 - 2023 **Module of legal and socio-techincal aspects of blockchain and cryptocurrencies**, *Diverse programs*, Université Paris I Panthéon-Sorbonne Taught the module of legal and socio-techincal aspects for different course levels

(undergraduate, masters) in the Blockchain course.

#### 2020 - 2023 Module of privacy and Data Protection Requirements, Diverse programs.

Université Paris I Panthéon-Sorbonne

Taught the module of privacy and data protection requirements for different course levels (undergraduate, masters) in the Requirement Engineering course

#### 2021 Ciberterrorism.

American Bar Association Rule of Law Initiative

Course for lawyers, public prosecutors, police and other public servants from Perú, where we covered the definition of ciberterrorism and studied ciberattacks analysis in the peruvian legislation

#### 2020 **Open Source Intelligence Class**, *Diploma Intelligence and Prospective*.

**FLACSO** 

3 hours course for the Diploma Intelligence and Prospective. Taught about open-source intelligence and its methodology

## Teaching assistant.

The work consisted on helping in the creation of exams questions and correction guidelines, exams marking and teaching.

#### 2016-2017 Themes of Strategic Analysis, Prof. Ricardo Neeb.

Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile

Introductory course to the themes of strategy, such as grand-strategy, conflict and war, the evolution of war, State intelligence and the impact in international relations.

# 2016 **Defence Policy and its challenge in the International Scheme**, *Prof. Ricardo Need*. Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile

Public policy course, that aims to teach - under the comparative method - the creation of defence and security State policy.

#### 2016 **Theory of International Relations**, *Prof. Dr. Carsten Schulz*.

Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile

A specialized course in studying the mainstream school of thoughts in international relations, such as liberalism, realism, critical theory, among others.

#### 2015 **Political Development of Central and Eastern Europe**, *Prof. Dr. Euvgenia Fediakova*.

Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile

The course studies the socio-political events from 1918 to 1992 in the Soviet Union , Yugoslavia and other central and eastern european countries

# Public outreach: Articles [scientific], talks, and news

September 2023 **Portal2EU policy presentation**, *The Europaeum*, Berlin, Germany.

# April 2023 **Requirements engineerings, reuglation and data protection**, *Invited to present by IREB*, Paris, France.

- March 2023 **Security requirements engineering**, *Invited to the World Trade Organization digital commerce working group*, Geneva, Switzerland.
- February 2023 **Interview about USA and EU "ban" of TikTok on official devices**, *DW News Latinamerica*, [Online].
- November 2022 **Regulation of cryptography**, *Invited to present by the Chilean delegation to the World Trade Organization*, Geneva, Switzerland [Online].

- November 2022 **Small interview about Twitter's situation and cibersecurity challenges**, *DW News Latinamerica*, [Online].
  - October 2022 **Evidence based policy module for "Gestión de Datos en el Sector Público"**, *organized by OptIA and Laboratorio de Gobierno* [*Chilean governmental institution*], Santiago, Chile [Online].
- September 2022 **Woman in Technology Hacking, blockchain, and gender trolling,** *Woman in eDiscovery* [*Chilean chapter*], Santiago, Chile [Online].
  - May 2022 **Legal Challenges of Blockchain Technology**, Segundo Congreso de Derecho y Tecnología, Universidad de Chile, Santiago, Chile.
- November 2021 Radio participation for analyzing the Chilean bill 'las plataformas de servicios digitales en Chile, así como de los usuarios de ellas' Boletín N. 14561-19, Radio USACH, Santiago, Chile.
- September 2021 Data protection and blockchain system, Blockchain Stampede, Lyon, France.
  - July 2021 Data protection for blockchain systems: the creation of compliant systems and public-interest technologist, *Lockdown Chile*, Chile.
  - April 2021 **La protección de datos en un mundo interconectado desde unamirada tecnologica interdisciplinaria**, *Mujeres liderando la tecnología*, Instituto de Ciencias Tecnológicas, Chile.
  - April 2021 **Part of the roundtable "Algoritmos e IA"**, *La Agenda Digital en la Nueva Constitución*, Senado de Chile, la Subsecretaría del Interior, el Observatorio Público para la Transparencia e Inclusión Algorítmica, Derechos Digital, Datos Protegidos, el Centro de Sistemas Públicos, el Instituto Desafíos de la Democracia, el Instituto Mileno de los Datos y el Consejo Chileno de Tecnologías de la Información y Comunicaciones, Chile.
  - February 2021 **Transparent and inclusive algorithms in a new constitution**, *Verano de datos abiertos constituyentesl*, FLACSO, Universidad de Chile, Consejo para la Transparencia and others, Chile.
    - October 2020 Requirements for human values and moral situations: Towards and ethical AI?, l CONGRESO INTERNACIONAL EN ALGORITMOS, INTELIGENCIA ARTIFICIAL, PERFILAMIENTO E IDENTIDAD DIGITAL., Universidad de Buenos Aires, Argentina.
      - June 2020 **Towards interdisciplinarity in technology and the role of public interest technologist**, *Ciclo Privacidad y Nueva Normalidad sesión 1*, Universidad de Chile, Chile.

### Languages

**Spanish**: Native **English**: Bilingual

French: B2 level

IB A2 Higher Level, ToEFL (expired)

### Voluntary work

07/2022–12/2022 **Collaborator of the AI legislative working group**, *Senate*, Chile.

Collaborator of the working group for the Chilean AI legislative process, as a representative of OptIA.

07/2022–12/2022 Collaborator of the cibersecurity working group, Senate, Chile.

Ocassional collaborator of the working group for the new Chilean cibersecurity bill, as a representative of OptIA. Specific working group: "Investigación Avanzada en

Ciberseguridad"

09/2020–04/2022 **Collaborator**, Fundación Datos Protegidos, Chile.

Collaborating in the work of the data protection and privacy chilean NGO "Datos Protegidos". Worked carried out consist of analyzing chilean policy and it's implication, technical discussion about data protection, participation in forums and others

01/2015–10/2016 **Founder and Vice-President**, *Laboratorio de Diplolmacia (DiploLab)*, Chile.

DiploLab was a NGO that promoted youth talent in diplomacy and international relations. Spokeswoman, fundraiser and community manager.

### Skills

Advanced Security & privacy impact assessment, research & analysis, qualitative methodology, requirements engineering, policy building and analysis, human-computer interaction Intermediate Python, CSS, conceptual modeling, risk analysis, quantitative methodology Basic SQL, Node.JS, R, graphic design, Javascript